<VerificationPlan VERSION="1.0.0">
  <GlobalPolicy>
    <log-format>[ModuleName][functionName][BLOCK_NAME] message</log-format>
    <deterministic-first>true</deterministic-first>
    <split-topology-policy>Phase 1 verification must prove that the HTTP server is the sole runtime/model host while Telegram acts only as a remote HTTP client and CLI stays out of Phase 1 unless a blocker forces inclusion.</split-topology-policy>
    <anti-local-fallback-policy>Phase 1 evidence must reject any Telegram or CLI path that implies local model hosting, local inference fallback, or alternate runtime ownership outside the HTTP server.</anti-local-fallback-policy>
    <module-level-focus>Fast deterministic checks close to the module using pytest -m unit.</module-level-focus>
    <wave-level-focus>Integration checks for adapter wiring and endpoint behavior using pytest -m integration.</wave-level-focus>
    <phase-level-focus>Full regression suite including architecture boundary checks using pytest.</phase-level-focus>
    <redaction>Never log secrets, credentials, bearer tokens, or raw audio payloads.</redaction>
  </GlobalPolicy>

  <CriticalFlows>
    <VF-001 NAME="SyncTTSHappyPath" USE_CASES="UC-001" DATA_FLOW="DF-SYNC-TTS" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>API client submits a valid custom TTS request through the HTTP adapter and receives audio.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>WAV audio bytes are returned with 200 status, request context is preserved, and route-level inference markers are emitted.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <log-marker>[RoutesTTS][openai_speech][BLOCK_LOG_OPENAI_REQUEST]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_EXECUTE_SYNTHESIS]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_LOG_INFERENCE_COMPLETION]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[Responses][build_audio_response][BUILD_AUDIO_RESPONSE]</log-marker>
        <trace-sequence>[RoutesTTS][openai_speech][BLOCK_LOG_OPENAI_REQUEST] -> [RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_EXECUTE_SYNTHESIS] -> [RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_LOG_INFERENCE_COMPLETION] -> [Responses][build_audio_response][BUILD_AUDIO_RESPONSE]</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-001>

    <VF-002 NAME="CloneTTSHappyPath" USE_CASES="UC-003" DATA_FLOW="DF-CLONE-TTS" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>API client submits a valid clone request with reference audio and receives cloned audio.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Reference audio is normalized when needed, clone synthesis completes, and the response returns WAV audio.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <log-marker>[RoutesTTS][tts_clone][BLOCK_LOG_CLONE_REQUEST]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[TTSService][synthesize_clone][BLOCK_PREPARE_REFERENCE_AUDIO]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[TTSService][synthesize_clone][BLOCK_EXECUTE_CLONE]</log-marker>
        <log-marker>[TTSService][_run_generation][BLOCK_PERSIST_OUTPUT]</log-marker>
        <trace-sequence>[RoutesTTS][tts_clone][BLOCK_LOG_CLONE_REQUEST] -> [TTSService][synthesize_clone][BLOCK_PREPARE_REFERENCE_AUDIO] -> [TTSService][synthesize_clone][BLOCK_EXECUTE_CLONE] -> [TTSService][_run_generation][BLOCK_PERSIST_OUTPUT]</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-002>

    <VF-003 NAME="AsyncJobLifecycle" USE_CASES="UC-004" DATA_FLOW="DF-ASYNC-JOB" PRIORITY="medium">
      <scenario>Client submits an async job, polls status, and retrieves the completed audio result.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Job ID is returned immediately, status transitions through queued/running/terminal states, and result retrieval returns audio bytes.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>POST /v1/audio/speech/jobs -> queued snapshot -> running or succeeded snapshot -> GET /api/v1/tts/jobs/{job_id}/result returns audio payload</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-003>

    <VF-004 NAME="BackendAutoselection" USE_CASES="UC-008" DATA_FLOW="DF-BACKEND-SELECTION" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>Runtime starts with explicit or autoselect backend configuration and resolves an operational backend.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>BackendRegistry chooses a usable backend and ModelRegistry readiness reporting exposes selected backend and model availability.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>BackendRegistry chooses explicit or autoselected backend -> ModelRegistry readiness_report exposes selected backend and available models</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-004>
    <VF-011 NAME="EnginePlanningReadiness" USE_CASES="UC-008" DATA_FLOW="DF-BACKEND-SELECTION,DF-REQUEST-TO-PLAN" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>Engine planning surfaces can resolve a family, engine, and backend path without breaking current transport behavior.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Engine registry and compatibility bridge evidence show the planned engine vocabulary, typed config, TTSEngine, and worker pool while current runtime paths remain intact.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>Discovery resolves engine-related modules -> engine config parses typed settings -> engine registry resolves engine strategy -> bridge adapts current family surfaces -> scheduler keeps worker pool dispatch explicit</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-011>

    <VF-005 NAME="RequestToPlanFlow" USE_CASES="UC-001,UC-002,UC-003" DATA_FLOW="DF-REQUEST-TO-PLAN" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>A normalized synthesis request is resolved through planner, family adapter, runtime model registry, and backend execution without transport-specific branching.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Planner produces an execution plan, the family adapter prepares backend execution inputs, and the coordinator returns a persisted GenerationResult while preserving observability markers.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>Synthesis coordinator normalizes request -> planner resolves capability and backend -> runtime model registry provides handle -> backend executes -> coordinator persists output</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-005>

    <VF-006 NAME="HostAwareReadiness" USE_CASES="UC-008" DATA_FLOW="DF-STARTUP-READINESS" PRIORITY="high">
      <scenario>Runtime startup exposes host-aware readiness that distinguishes host, backend, catalog, artifact, and runtime states with explicit rejection reasons.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Readiness payload explains why candidates are accepted or rejected and no longer relies solely on platform-order heuristics.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>Host probe captures runtime features -> backend diagnostics collected -> catalog and artifact states evaluated -> readiness report exposes accepted and rejected candidates with reasons</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-006>

    <VF-007 NAME="SecondFamilyOnboarding" USE_CASES="UC-001,UC-002,UC-003" DATA_FLOW="DF-NEW-FAMILY-ONBOARDING" PRIORITY="medium">
      <scenario>A second model family is added without transport adapter rewrites and is resolved through the same planner and backend contracts.</scenario>
      <expected-outcome>Second-family tests pass, planner integration remains generic, and transport adapters remain untouched except for any optional product-surface exposure explicitly approved later.</expected-outcome>
      <required-signals>
        <trace-sequence>New family adapter registered -> planner resolves family through existing capability contracts -> integration tests pass without adapter boundary regressions</trace-sequence>
      </required-signals>
    </VF-007>
#AC|    <VF-008 NAME="SplitTopologyPhase1" USE_CASES="UC-001,UC-004,UC-008" DATA_FLOW="DF-SYNC-TTS,DF-ASYNC-JOB,DF-TELEGRAM-TTS" PRIORITY="high">
#UV|      <scenario>Phase 1 architecture evidence proves the HTTP server owns runtime and model hosting while Telegram only forwards work to the server over HTTP and CLI remains out of the Phase 1 host path.</scenario>
#MH|      <expected-outcome>Server startup, health, and readiness evidence prove local runtime ownership on the HTTP server only, and Telegram evidence shows remote submission or delivery behavior without any Telegram-side local inference host implication.</expected-outcome>
#VP|      <required-signals>
#RS|        <trace-sequence>HTTP server health and readiness probes show local host ownership -> Telegram update handling emits remote HTTP client behavior -> no Telegram-side model host or inference fallback evidence appears</trace-sequence>
#NP|        <log-marker>[RoutesTTS][openai_speech][BLOCK_LOG_OPENAI_REQUEST]</log-marker>
#TG|        <evidence-note>Server startup and readiness evidence are taken from the existing server health/readiness flows rather than a fabricated build marker.</evidence-note>
#MK|        <evidence-note>Telegram evidence must remain limited to remote HTTP client behavior and delivery pathways.</evidence-note>
#TF|      </required-signals>
#ZT|    </VF-008>

#UP|    <VF-009 NAME="AntiLocalFallbackPhase1" USE_CASES="UC-001,UC-002,UC-003" DATA_FLOW="DF-TELEGRAM-TTS,DF-CLI-TTS" PRIORITY="high">
#RA|      <scenario>Telegram and CLI paths must not silently host local inference or fall back to a local model when the HTTP server is the only Phase 1 runtime host.</scenario>
#MQ|      <expected-outcome>Any evidence of Telegram-side or CLI-side local runtime ownership, direct backend execution, or fallback-to-local-model behavior fails the gate, while remote HTTP submission and server-side execution pass.</expected-outcome>
#VP|      <required-signals>
#RS|        <trace-sequence>Telegram or CLI request -> remote HTTP contract only -> server executes inference -> no local fallback branch on Telegram or CLI</trace-sequence>
#LM|        <evidence-note>Telegram evidence must stay within remote client behavior and must not imply local inference, local model registry ownership, or alternate runtime fallback.</evidence-note>
#FC|        <evidence-note>CLI evidence must remain out of Phase 1 unless explicitly blocked in the plan, and must not be used as local runtime evidence for the central-server target state.</evidence-note>
#TN|        <forbidden-signal>Any log or test evidence that constructs or selects a local inference backend, local job executor, or model registry as host-owned runtime outside the HTTP server</forbidden-signal>
#TF|      </required-signals>
#ZX|    </VF-009>
#NN|    <VF-010 NAME="Phase1CutoverGuardrails" USE_CASES="UC-001,UC-004,UC-008" DATA_FLOW="DF-REQUEST-TO-PLAN,DF-SYNC-TTS,DF-TELEGRAM-TTS" PRIORITY="high">
#RV|      <scenario>Operators roll out Phase 1 by bringing the server up first, then Telegram, then any other remote clients, and they can prove the migration with paired server and client evidence.</scenario>
#YY|      <expected-outcome>Documentation and validation evidence show the canonical HTTP server contract as the source of truth, client cutover happens only after server readiness is verified, rollback happens by stopping or repointing clients before server recovery, and `telegram-live` is treated as boundary proof rather than server-execution proof by itself.</expected-outcome>
#QT|      <required-signals>
#BP|        <trace-sequence>Server readiness evidence -> Telegram boundary evidence -> paired server and client artifacts -> migration declared good only after both sides are present</trace-sequence>
#XR|        <evidence-note>Server evidence must include readiness and model discovery proof from the same deployment window or an equivalent validated command output.</evidence-note>
#NW|        <evidence-note>Telegram evidence must include `telegram-live` output and retained client-side logs or compose/service logs from the same cutover window.</evidence-note>
#RT|        <evidence-note>Rollback evidence must show clients being stopped or repointed before server recovery and client restart only after readiness returns.</evidence-note>
#QH|        <forbidden-signal>Any wording or evidence that presents Phase 1 as public-internet ready, implies the CLI is migrated in Phase 1, or allows Telegram to silently infer local runtime ownership.</forbidden-signal>
#QH|      </required-signals>
#BZ|    </VF-010>
  </CriticalFlows>

  <ModuleVerification>
    <V-M-CONFIG MODULE="M-CONFIG" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_api.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py -m unit</check-1>
        <check-2>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py tests/integration/test_api.py -m "unit or integration"</check-2>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Default settings use local runtime defaults for job backends, auth, manifest path, preload policy, rate limiting, and quota.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Canonical `TTS_*` environment variables override manifest, preload, auth, rate-limit, and quota settings with normalized values.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Explicit models, outputs, voices, and upload staging directories are parsed into the resulting settings object.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Runtime capability bindings for family, custom, design, and clone models are parsed from environment variables as active runtime configuration rather than inferred artifact presence.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">When a capability binding is configured, requests without an explicit model resolve through the runtime-bound model for that execution mode.</scenario-5>
        <scenario-6 kind="failure">When a capability binding is missing, the API returns a controlled runtime capability error instead of falling back to another local model.</scenario-6>
        <scenario-7 kind="success">Launcher and readiness surfaces expose the runtime capability map explicitly so adapters can distinguish bound capabilities from local artifact presence.</scenario-7>
        <scenario-8 kind="success">CLI, Telegram, and the frontend demo consume runtime capability bindings instead of requiring explicit model identifiers in normal runtime-bound flows.</scenario-8>
        <scenario-9 kind="success">Configuration uses the `TTS_*` namespace exclusively across runtime, validation, and operator surfaces.</scenario-9>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-CONFIG>

    <V-M-ERRORS MODULE="M-ERRORS" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_audio_sender_client.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_audio_sender_client.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="failure">Backend selection and model affinity failures surface typed BackendNotAvailableError, BackendCapabilityError, and ModelNotAvailableError cases.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="failure">Conflicting async job idempotency reuse raises JobIdempotencyConflictError.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="failure">MLX runtime loading failures surface ModelLoadError with detailed diagnostic context.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="failure">Telegram audio conversion failures surface AudioConversionError without hiding the root cause.</scenario-4>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ERRORS>

    <V-M-OBSERVABILITY MODULE="M-OBSERVABILITY" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_api.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py tests/integration/test_api.py -m "unit or integration"</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Structured request logs include request_id, path, status, and endpoint context for HTTP flows.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="failure">Timeout and worker-failure logs preserve request_id and inference_operation context.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">TTS service structured logs include mode, text length, language, and persistence context for clone synthesis.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[ServerApp][request_context_middleware][BLOCK_LOG_REQUEST_START]</marker-1>
        <marker-2>[ServerApp][request_context_middleware][BLOCK_LOG_SUCCESS_RESPONSE]</marker-2>
        <marker-3>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_HANDLE_INFERENCE_TIMEOUT]</marker-3>
        <marker-4>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_HANDLE_INFERENCE_FAILURE]</marker-4>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-OBSERVABILITY>

    <V-M-METRICS MODULE="M-METRICS" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_metrics_observability.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_metrics_observability.py tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Execution metrics collect submitted, started, completed, and queue-depth counters through the local job manager lifecycle.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">MLX metrics collect cache hits, cache misses, load durations, and load failures.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Server readiness reporting exposes the operational metrics snapshot from the runtime registry.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-METRICS>

    <V-M-CONTRACTS MODULE="M-CONTRACTS" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Async job submissions preserve operation, request_id, owner principal, and execution timeout metadata.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">InMemoryJobExecutor dispatches command DTOs across custom, design, and clone operations.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">VoiceCloneCommand and GenerationResult remain compatible with the TTS service clone flow and structured log assertions.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-CONTRACTS>

    <V-M-MODELS MODULE="M-MODELS" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Manifest metadata and artifact validation rules remain consistent with the currently supported backends.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Model manifest loading preserves rollout preference and enabled-model filtering semantics.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-MODELS>

    <V-M-EXECUTION-PLAN MODULE="M-EXECUTION-PLAN" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Normalized synthesis capability and execution-plan contracts preserve enough information to drive planner, family, and backend execution.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Compatibility wrappers from current command DTOs preserve existing transport-facing behavior.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-EXECUTION-PLAN>

    <V-M-HOST-PROBE MODULE="M-HOST-PROBE" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_host_probe.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_host_probe.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Host probe distinguishes OS, architecture, runtime dependencies, and accelerator hints relevant to backend planning.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Missing runtime features are exposed as diagnostics rather than silently folded into model availability.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-HOST-PROBE>

    <V-M-MODEL-FAMILY MODULE="M-MODEL-FAMILY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_qwen3_family_adapter.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_qwen3_family_adapter.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Family adapters match capabilities and translate normalized requests into backend execution inputs without transport involvement.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-MODEL-FAMILY>

    <V-M-QWEN3-FAMILY MODULE="M-QWEN3-FAMILY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_qwen3_family_adapter.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_qwen3_family_adapter.py tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Current Qwen3 custom, design, and clone semantics are preserved after extraction into an explicit family adapter.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Family-specific metadata no longer needs to live in generic catalog surfaces except for compatibility wrappers that are intentionally documented.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-QWEN3-FAMILY>

    <V-M-OMNIVOICE-FAMILY MODULE="M-OMNIVOICE-FAMILY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_model_families.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_model_families.py tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">OmniVoice family plans preserve custom, design, and clone capability mapping without transport-specific branching.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-OMNIVOICE-FAMILY>

    <V-M-BACKENDS MODULE="M-BACKENDS" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_qwen_fast_backend.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py tests/unit/core/test_qwen_fast_backend.py tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">BackendRegistry honors explicit backend selection and autoselection preference ordering.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="failure">Unsupported mode, missing local artifacts, and backend-affinity mismatches raise typed capability or availability errors.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Manifest artifact validation rules match the runtime requirements expected by MLX, accelerated Qwen fast, and Torch backends.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Listed preload policy preloads requested models and exposes cache diagnostics through the registry surface.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="failure">MLX normalized runtime loading fails fast with ModelLoadError when tokenizer initialization is incomplete.</scenario-5>
        <scenario-6 kind="failure">Accelerated Qwen backend exposes explicit readiness rejection reasons for custom, design, and clone when its fast prerequisites are missing.</scenario-6>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-BACKENDS>
    <V-M-ENGINE-CONTRACTS MODULE="M-ENGINE-CONTRACTS" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_engine_contracts.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_engine_contracts.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Engine handle, TTSEngine, EngineCapabilities, SynthesisJob, AudioBuffer, and EngineAvailability contracts stay explicit and reusable across family and backend planning surfaces.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-CONTRACTS>

    <V-M-ENGINE-CONFIG MODULE="M-ENGINE-CONFIG" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_engine_config.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_engine_config.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Engine configuration parsing keeps the planned registry and scheduler settings explicit in typed config.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-CONFIG>

    <V-M-ENGINE-REGISTRY MODULE="M-ENGINE-REGISTRY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_engine_registry.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_engine_registry.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Engine discovery and resolution remain deterministic and fail fast when no compatible engine exists in the engine registry.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-REGISTRY>

    <V-M-ENGINE-BRIDGE MODULE="M-ENGINE-BRIDGE" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_engine_bridge.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_engine_bridge.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Compatibility bridge adapts family requests and backend results without changing transport-facing behavior.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-BRIDGE>

    <V-M-ENGINE-SCHEDULER MODULE="M-ENGINE-SCHEDULER" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_engine_scheduler.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_engine_scheduler.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Scheduler dispatch stays bounded, observable, and explicit about queueing decisions through the worker pool.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-SCHEDULER>

    <V-M-ENGINE-ROUTE-SPLIT MODULE="M-ENGINE-ROUTE-SPLIT" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/architecture/test_engine_route_split.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_engine_route_split.py -m architecture</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Route split keeps engine planning separate from transport adapters and does not add a public API rewrite.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-ROUTE-SPLIT>

    <V-M-ENGINE-MIGRATION-CLEANUP MODULE="M-ENGINE-ROUTE-SPLIT" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/architecture/test_engine_migration_cleanup.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_engine_migration_cleanup.py -m architecture</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Migration cleanup verifies that the planning wave does not leave behind duplicate concepts or stale route ownership claims.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-MIGRATION-CLEANUP>

    <V-M-ENGINE-STATIC-COUPLING MODULE="M-ENGINE-REGISTRY" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/architecture/test_engine_static_coupling.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_engine_static_coupling.py -m architecture</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Static coupling checks confirm the new engine docs stay declarative and do not introduce runtime dependencies.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ENGINE-STATIC-COUPLING>

    <V-M-INFRASTRUCTURE MODULE="M-INFRASTRUCTURE" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_admission_control.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py tests/unit/core/test_admission_control.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">LocalInMemoryJobStore creates, transitions, cancels, purges, and replays async job snapshots deterministically.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">LocalBoundedExecutionManager executes jobs to success, handles timeouts, rejects queue overflow, and enforces cancellation rules.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">LocalJobArtifactHandler removes staged input files during terminal cleanup.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Local rate limiting and quota guards remain principal-scoped and deterministic under parallel contention.</scenario-4>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-INFRASTRUCTURE>

    <V-M-MODEL-REGISTRY MODULE="M-MODEL-REGISTRY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">ModelRegistry readiness_report reflects listed preload policy, loaded model ids, and cache diagnostics.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Readiness reporting marks preloaded models as loaded in per-item preload metadata.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Readiness reporting exposes fast-lane route candidates and fallback reasons for Qwen custom, design, and clone models without contaminating other families.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[ModelRegistry][get_model][GET_MODEL]</marker-1>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-MODEL-REGISTRY>

    <V-M-MODEL-CATALOG MODULE="M-MODEL-CATALOG" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Catalog metadata distinguishes stable public model IDs from local artifact folder paths.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Catalog metadata can represent family-aware capabilities without regressing current Qwen3 manifest support.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-MODEL-CATALOG>

    <V-M-ARTIFACT-REGISTRY MODULE="M-ARTIFACT-REGISTRY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Artifact registry distinguishes declared catalog entries from installed and loadable artifact layouts.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="failure">Missing artifacts surface as explicit artifact-state failures rather than as missing catalog entries.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ARTIFACT-REGISTRY>

    <V-M-RUNTIME-MODEL-REGISTRY MODULE="M-RUNTIME-MODEL-REGISTRY" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Runtime model registry owns preload and cache state independently from catalog metadata.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Runtime model registry exposes loaded, runtime-ready, and preload state clearly in readiness surfaces.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-RUNTIME-MODEL-REGISTRY>

    <V-M-CAPABILITY-RESOLVER MODULE="M-CAPABILITY-RESOLVER" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Capability resolver exposes why a family, backend, or host combination is accepted or rejected.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Readiness surfaces can show capability-based rejection reasons without transport-specific logic.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-CAPABILITY-RESOLVER>

    <V-M-SYNTHESIS-PLANNER MODULE="M-SYNTHESIS-PLANNER" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_synthesis_planner.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Planner resolves normalized requests into family, model, backend, and artifact decisions without breaking current Qwen3 flows.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Planner remains orchestration logic only and does not absorb persistence or transport policy responsibilities.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-SYNTHESIS-PLANNER>

    <V-M-BACKENDS-V2 MODULE="M-BACKENDS-V2" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_qwen_fast_backend.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py tests/unit/core/test_qwen_fast_backend.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Generic backend execution contracts preserve current Qwen3 behavior through family adapters.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Backend diagnostics and cache state remain explicit after backend-interface generalization.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="failure">Qwen fast backend remains additive and fallback-safe inside the generic execution contract for custom, design, and clone.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-BACKENDS-V2>

    <V-M-TTS-SERVICE MODULE="M-TTS-SERVICE" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Clone synthesis passes the reference audio path to backend generation as a normalized string.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Explicit language values are normalized before clone synthesis is executed.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Structured clone logs include the entry marker and persistence marker with mode, model, and language context.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[TTSService][synthesize_clone][SYNTHESIZE_CLONE]</marker-1>
        <marker-2>[TTSService][synthesize_clone][BLOCK_PREPARE_REFERENCE_AUDIO]</marker-2>
        <marker-3>[TTSService][_run_generation][BLOCK_PERSIST_OUTPUT]</marker-3>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-TTS-SERVICE>

    <V-M-TTS-COORDINATOR MODULE="M-TTS-COORDINATOR" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_api.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py tests/integration/test_api.py -m "unit or integration"</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Coordinator-shaped service preserves inference guard, persistence, and logging while delegating planning and family semantics.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Current transport-facing flows remain behaviorally compatible after coordinator refactor.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-TTS-COORDINATOR>

    <V-M-APPLICATION MODULE="M-APPLICATION" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">JobExecutionGateway delegates to the store when no manager is configured.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">JobExecutionGateway delegates submit and cancel operations to the configured manager when present.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">InMemoryJobExecutor dispatches custom, design, and clone operations to the application service by operation type.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-APPLICATION>

    <V-M-BOOTSTRAP MODULE="M-BOOTSTRAP" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py</file>
        <file>tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_validate_runtime.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_family_env_guidance.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py -m "unit or architecture"</check-1>
        <check-2>python scripts/runtime_self_check.py</check-2>
        <check-3>python scripts/validate_runtime.py host-matrix</check-3>
        <check-4>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py tests/unit/scripts/test_family_env_guidance.py -m unit</check-4>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">build_runtime passes manifest path and preload configuration into backend and registry wiring.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Local job artifact, metadata, and execution factories preserve the local default runtime wiring.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="failure">Unsupported job backend identifiers are rejected by the bootstrap wiring factories.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Architecture checks keep bootstrap wiring config-driven and free of adapter-layer drift.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">Operator self-check outputs selected backend, per-model execution backend, host snapshot, and missing asset evidence without import-path failures.</scenario-5>
        <scenario-6 kind="success">Operator self-check exposes qwen_fast enablement, test-mode overrides, route candidates, and fallback reasons when the accelerated lane is configured.</scenario-6>
        <scenario-7 kind="success">Host-matrix validation automates baseline and simulated qwen_fast lane evidence so support claims stay synchronized with runtime diagnostics.</scenario-7>
        <scenario-8 kind="success">Windows Docker Desktop validation can reuse the same runtime wiring with Linux containers after the container trust store includes the required corporate proxy root certificate.</scenario-8>
        <scenario-9 kind="success">Operator self-check exposes family, module, and dedicated isolated-environment guidance through the shared profiles package surface without import-boundary drift.</scenario-9>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-BOOTSTRAP>

    <V-M-DOCKER-ASSETS MODULE="M-DOCKER-ASSETS" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>server/Dockerfile</file>
        <file>telegram_bot/Dockerfile</file>
        <file>docker-compose.server.yaml</file>
        <file>docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml</file>
        <file>docker/certs/infowatch-transparent-proxy-root.crt</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>docker compose -f docker-compose.server.yaml build</check-1>
        <check-2>docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml build</check-2>
        <check-3>docker compose -f docker-compose.server.yaml up -d server</check-3>
        <check-4>docker exec tts-server-server-1 python -c "import urllib.request; print(urllib.request.urlopen('http://127.0.0.1:8000/health/live').read().decode())"</check-4>
        <check-5>docker exec tts-server-server-1 python -c "import urllib.request; print(urllib.request.urlopen('http://127.0.0.1:8000/health/ready').read().decode())"</check-5>
        <check-6>docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml up -d telegram-bot</check-6>
        <check-7>docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml logs --no-color telegram-bot</check-7>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Server Docker image build succeeds on the current Windows host with Docker Desktop Linux containers.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Container trust-store wiring includes the required corporate proxy root certificate so Python HTTPS package installation succeeds behind the daemon proxy.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Server compose runtime exposes healthy `/health/live`, `/health/ready`, and `/api/v1/models` responses while mounted models, outputs, uploads, voices, and ffmpeg remain visible inside the container.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Telegram compose runtime remains documented as a lane, but current retained evidence does not claim it as proven on this host.</scenario-4>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-DOCKER-ASSETS>

    <V-M-SERVER MODULE="M-SERVER" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/integration/test_api.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_backend_api_metadata.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py</file>
        <file>tests/smoke/test_local_runtime.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py tests/unit/server/test_tts_routes.py -m "integration or unit"</check-1>
        <check-1a>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py tests/integration/test_backend_api_metadata.py -m "integration"</check-1a>
        <check-2>TTS_RUN_SMOKE=1 python -m pytest tests/smoke/test_local_runtime.py -m smoke</check-2>
        <check-3>TTS_RUN_SMOKE=1 TTS_SMOKE_MODEL_ID=Qwen3-TTS-12Hz-1.7B-CustomVoice-8bit python -m pytest tests/smoke/test_local_runtime.py -m smoke</check-3>
        <check-4>TTS_RUN_SMOKE=1 TTS_SMOKE_MODEL_ID=Piper-en_US-lessac-medium TTS_SMOKE_EXPECTED_BACKEND=onnx python -m pytest tests/smoke/test_local_runtime.py -m smoke</check-4>
        <check-5>python scripts/validate_runtime.py smoke-server</check-5>
        <check-6>python scripts/validate_runtime.py smoke-server --smoke-model-id Piper-en_US-lessac-medium --expected-backend onnx</check-6>
        <check-7>docker compose -f docker-compose.server.yaml up -d server</check-7>
        <check-8>docker exec tts-server-server-1 python -c "import urllib.request; print(urllib.request.urlopen('http://127.0.0.1:8000/health/live').read().decode())"</check-8>
        <check-9>docker exec tts-server-server-1 python -c "import urllib.request; print(urllib.request.urlopen('http://127.0.0.1:8000/health/ready').read().decode())"</check-9>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Health live and readiness endpoints expose expected status plus deep readiness diagnostics.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">OpenAI-compatible, custom, design, and clone HTTP endpoints return audio and propagate request metadata.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">Async submit, status, result, cancel, and idempotency flows remain deterministic through the HTTP adapter, with stable `x-job-id` and `x-submit-request-id` headers across submission and later lifecycle reads.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="failure">Unified HTTP error responses cover validation failures, rate limits, timeouts, worker failures, and ownership checks.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-4a kind="success">The Phase 1 canonical remote contract is explicit: `/v1/audio/speech` is the canonical sync speech contract, `/v1/audio/speech/jobs` is the canonical async submit contract for that payload, and `/api/v1/tts/jobs/{job_id}` resources remain the canonical async job resource URLs.</scenario-4a>
        <scenario-4b kind="success">Async job snapshots expose only the official public lifecycle states `queued`, `running`, `succeeded`, `failed`, and `cancelled`.</scenario-4b>
        <scenario-4d kind="failure">Bounded sync execution is explicit and non-fallback: timed-out sync requests return `504 request_timeout`, while async execution remains reachable only through the existing job-submit routes.</scenario-4d>
        <scenario-4c kind="failure">Controlled HTTP failures always use the shared machine-readable envelope with `code`, `message`, `details`, and `request_id`.</scenario-4c>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">Request, inference, and response logs include request_id and GRACE block markers for observability assertions.</scenario-5>
        <scenario-6 kind="failure">Unsupported family and operation combinations return controlled model_capability_not_supported errors instead of ambiguous runtime failures.</scenario-6>
        <scenario-7 kind="success">Readiness and model discovery payloads expose selected backend, per-model execution backend, routing reasons, and family capability metadata for mixed-family deployments.</scenario-7>
        <scenario-8 kind="success">Fast-lane metadata exposes `qwen_fast` as an explicit route candidate for Qwen custom, design, and clone modes with deterministic fallback reasons.</scenario-8>
        <scenario-9 kind="success">Automated smoke validation can start the local server, wait for healthy startup, execute smoke pytest, and stop the runtime cleanly without manual orchestration.</scenario-9>
        <scenario-10 kind="success">Smoke validation remains Qwen custom sync/async capable by default while supporting an explicit Piper smoke model path through the same public HTTP API with ONNX backend assertions.</scenario-10>
        <scenario-11 kind="success">On the current Windows host, server Docker deployment starts successfully and returns `status=ok` from `/health/live`, `/health/ready`, and `/api/v1/models`.</scenario-11>
        <scenario-12 kind="success">Server Docker readiness on the current Windows host confirms mounted `.models`, `.outputs`, `.uploads`, `.voices`, and in-container ffmpeg availability.</scenario-12>
#SR|        <scenario-13 kind="success">Phase 1 server evidence shows the HTTP server as the only local runtime/model host and keeps the canonical contract rooted at `/v1/audio/speech`, `/v1/audio/speech/jobs`, and `/api/v1/tts/jobs/{job_id}`.</scenario-13>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[ServerApp][request_context_middleware][BLOCK_LOG_REQUEST_START]</marker-1>
        <marker-2>[RoutesTTS][openai_speech][BLOCK_LOG_OPENAI_REQUEST]</marker-2>
        <marker-3>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_EXECUTE_SYNTHESIS]</marker-3>
        <marker-4>[Responses][build_audio_response][BUILD_AUDIO_RESPONSE]</marker-4>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-SERVER>

    <V-M-FRONTEND-DEMO MODULE="M-FRONTEND-DEMO" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>frontend_demo/index.html</file>
        <file>frontend_demo/app.js</file>
        <file>frontend_demo/styles.css</file>
        <file>frontend_demo/voice-presets.json</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m http.server 8030 -d .</check-1>
        <check-2>python scripts/validate_runtime.py smoke-server</check-2>
        <check-3>Browser verification loads the standalone demo, fetches `/health/ready`, submits `/api/v1/tts/clone`, and verifies playback/download state through the browser UI</check-3>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The standalone frontend module renders without server-owned static routes and loads local preset configuration from `voice-presets.json`.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">The frontend reads `/health/ready`, surfaces the active backend, and blocks clone submission when clone mode is unavailable.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">The frontend loads local reference audio, submits `multipart/form-data` to `/api/v1/tts/clone`, and exposes playback plus download after receiving `audio/wav`.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[ServerApp][request_context_middleware][BLOCK_LOG_REQUEST_START]</marker-1>
        <marker-2>[RoutesTTS][run_inference_with_timeout][BLOCK_EXECUTE_SYNTHESIS]</marker-2>
        <marker-3>[Responses][build_audio_response][BUILD_AUDIO_RESPONSE]</marker-3>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-FRONTEND-DEMO>

    <V-M-TELEGRAM MODULE="M-TELEGRAM" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_config_bootstrap.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_dispatcher.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_audio_sender_client.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_job_orchestrator.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_observability.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/test_telegram_bot/test_operational.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_remote_telegram_client.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_telegram_adapter/test_wiring.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_telegram_adapter/test_job_integration.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_telegram_adapter/test_delivery_recovery.py</file>
        <file>tests/architecture/test_no_telegram_local_runtime.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/test_telegram_bot -m unit</check-1>
        <check-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_telegram_adapter -m integration</check-2>
        <check-3>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_remote_telegram_client.py tests/architecture/test_no_telegram_local_runtime.py -m "unit or integration"</check-3>
        <check-4>TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL="$TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL" python scripts/validate_runtime.py telegram-live --bot-token "$TTS_TELEGRAM_BOT_TOKEN"</check-4>
        <check-5>TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL="$TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL" python scripts/validate_runtime.py telegram-live --bot-token "$TTS_TELEGRAM_BOT_TOKEN" --chat-id "$TTS_TELEGRAM_VALIDATION_CHAT_ID" --expect-update-chat-id "$TTS_TELEGRAM_VALIDATION_CHAT_ID" --expect-update-text "Qwen3-TTS validation ping."</check-5>
        <check-6>TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL="$TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL" docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml up -d telegram-bot</check-6>
        <check-7>docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml logs --no-color telegram-bot</check-7>
        <check-8>python scripts/validate_runtime.py docker-server</check-8>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">TelegramSettings.from_env and build_telegram_runtime validate configuration and assemble TelegramRuntime correctly.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">CommandDispatcher, TTSSynthesizer, PollingAdapter, TelegramSender, and TelegramBotClient remain correctly wired for adapter flows.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">DeliveryMetadataStore and TelegramJobOrchestrator preserve idempotency, completion polling, and restart recovery semantics.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Telegram audio conversion, voice upload formatting, and sender delegation remain contract-compatible.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">Telegram observability helpers emit structured GRACE event markers and polling metrics remain visible to tests.</scenario-5>
        <scenario-6 kind="success">Telegram live validation can verify Bot API reachability automatically when a real bot token is provided and can report the configured `TTS_TELEGRAM_SERVER_BASE_URL`, while remaining opt-in for secretless environments.</scenario-6>
        <scenario-7 kind="success">Telegram live validation can optionally send a validation ping and confirm that a newer matching inbound message update becomes visible through getUpdates for a dedicated test chat, while still reporting that server-side execution must be proven by companion server evidence.</scenario-7>
        <scenario-8 kind="success">The Telegram Docker compose lane remains documented and runnable, and its checks cover remote-server readiness wiring, startup self-checks, Bot API reachability, and polling behavior when the required bot token, remote server base URL, and validation context are available.</scenario-8>
        <scenario-9 kind="success">Telegram Docker runtime documentation preserves the adapter-local `.outputs` mount and the named `/app/.state` volume contract, does not imply local inference ownership inside the bot container, and keeps companion server evidence requirements explicit.</scenario-9>
#CJ|        <scenario-10 kind="success">Phase 1 Telegram evidence only demonstrates remote HTTP client behavior against the canonical server contract and never implies a local runtime or model host.</scenario-10>
#BZ|        <scenario-11 kind="failure">If Telegram logs, fixtures, or wiring evidence show local inference, local model registry ownership, or alternate runtime fallback, the split-topology gate fails.</scenario-11>
#QF|        <scenario-12 kind="success">A process-launched canonical HTTP stub can satisfy readiness, model discovery, sync speech, and async submit/status/result checks through the real Telegram remote client over loopback without in-process transports.</scenario-12>
#LX|        <scenario-13 kind="success">Architecture tests prove the migrated Telegram normal path requires a remote client, wires `synthesizer=None`, and routes `/tts`, `/design`, and `/clone` only through remote job orchestration.</scenario-13>
      </scenarios>
      <required-log-markers>
        <marker-1>[TelegramBootstrap][build_telegram_runtime][BLOCK_BUILD_RUNTIME]</marker-1>
        <marker-2>[Dispatcher][handle_update][BLOCK_LOG_INCOMING_UPDATE]</marker-2>
        <marker-3>[TTSHandler][synthesize][BLOCK_EXECUTE_TTS_SYNTHESIS]</marker-3>
        <marker-4>[JobOrchestrator][submit_tts_job][BLOCK_SUBMIT_JOB]</marker-4>
        <marker-5>[Poller][start][BLOCK_DISPATCH_UPDATES]</marker-5>
      </required-log-markers>
    </V-M-TELEGRAM>

    <V-M-CLI MODULE="M-CLI" PRIORITY="low">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/cli/test_runtime.py</file>
        <file>tests/integration/test_cli_launchability.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/cli/test_runtime.py -m unit</check-1>
        <check-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_cli_launchability.py -m integration</check-2>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">CLI runtime composes only core runtime services and the package entrypoint remains a thin wrapper.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">KeyboardInterrupt exits the CLI cleanly without surfacing spurious runtime errors.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">CLI launchability exposes the multi-family selection menu and bounded exit path through `python -m cli` without surfacing startup failures.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">OmniVoice design flows route through model metadata identifiers so capability-specific design synthesis stays family-aware.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">Automated CLI launchability evidence is retained as a transcript in `.sisyphus/evidence/cli-launchability-transcript.txt` after `python -m cli` receives scripted exit input.</scenario-5>
#QP|        <scenario-6 kind="success">CLI evidence stays out of the Phase 1 host split unless an explicit blocker reintroduces it, and the plan does not treat the CLI as a runtime/model host in the central-server target state.</scenario-6>
#PK|        <scenario-7 kind="failure">Any CLI evidence that constructs or implies a local runtime/model host for Phase 1 fails the anti-local-fallback gate.</scenario-7>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-CLI>

    <V-M-PROFILE-SCHEMA MODULE="M-PROFILE-SCHEMA" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">HostProfile, FamilyProfile, ModuleProfile, and ResolvedLaunchProfile serialize stable host, family, module, compatibility, backend, and metadata payloads for launcher consumers.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-PROFILE-SCHEMA>

    <V-M-PROFILE-RESOLVER MODULE="M-PROFILE-RESOLVER" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">ProfileResolver resolves family and module metadata into host-aware launch profiles with compatibility results, dependency-pack references, and expected interpreter paths.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">ProfileResolver can probe an isolated family environment and treat it as sufficient runtime evidence when host-level torch imports are unavailable.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">ProfileResolver compatibility results retain explicit incompatibility reasons when resolution marks a host contour or family dependency set as unsupported.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
      <coverage-notes>
        <note-1>Resolver coverage in this plan is limited to `tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py`; the scenarios above describe profile construction, isolated-environment probing, and compatibility payload details evidenced in that suite.</note-1>
      </coverage-notes>
    </V-M-PROFILE-RESOLVER>

    <V-M-PROFILES MODULE="M-PROFILES" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_family_env_guidance.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py tests/unit/scripts/test_family_env_guidance.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The public profiles package exports FamilyProfile, HostProfile, ModuleProfile, ProfileResolver, and ResolvedLaunchProfile for launcher and self-check tooling.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Dedicated family environment guidance for optional families remains exposed through the shared profile payload and package import boundary.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-PROFILES>

    <V-M-LAUNCHER MODULE="M-LAUNCHER" PRIORITY="high">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_plan_run.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_exec.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_launch.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_doctor.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_bootstrap_env.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_check_env.py</file>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_create_env.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_runtime_profiles.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_plan_run.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_exec.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_launch.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_doctor.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_bootstrap_env.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_check_env.py tests/unit/scripts/test_launcher_create_env.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">Launcher plan-run coverage, together with shared runtime profile assertions, preserves resolved family/module launch plans with dependency-pack previews, expected interpreter paths, and the canonical `family_environment` isolation policy.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">Launcher doctor, bootstrap-env, check-env, and create-env commands expose deterministic isolated-environment guidance, current implementation command previews, shared `.venv311` legacy detection, and `environment_isolated=true` for supported family contours.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="failure">Launcher exec reports missing isolated interpreters as structured JSON instead of opaque process failures and keeps the command rooted in `.envs/&lt;family&gt;` rather than a shared environment fallback.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">Create-env preview output retains the current implementation command strings, including Windows-oriented pip-safe path formatting and compiled requirements references for the selected family pack.</scenario-4>
        <scenario-5 kind="success">Launcher launch dispatches to the existing platform-specific interactive wrapper for the active host while preserving the Windows CMD compatibility path for signed-script constrained environments.</scenario-5>
      </scenarios>
      <coverage-notes>
        <note-1>Launcher coverage in this plan is limited to the listed unit suites; wording here is restricted to plan-run, exec, launch, doctor, bootstrap-env, check-env, create-env, and the `family_environment` one-family-one-environment payloads directly evidenced by those tests.</note-1>
      </coverage-notes>
    </V-M-LAUNCHER>
    <V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER MODULE="M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_windows_launcher_script.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_windows_launcher_script.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The Windows launcher script remains a thin orchestrator over the profile-aware Python launcher by reusing create-env, check-env, and exec flows instead of duplicating runtime resolution logic.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">The Windows launcher retains bounded family-aware download strategies: Hugging Face snapshot download for Qwen and OmniVoice plus the documented Piper downloader path for Piper voices.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">The Windows launcher keeps transient secret handling bounded to process-local HF and Telegram token prompts instead of persisting credentials to repository files.</scenario-3>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER>
    <V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-CMD MODULE="M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-CMD" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_windows_launcher_script.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_windows_launcher_script.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The Windows CMD wrapper remains a thin entrypoint that delegates to the PowerShell launcher without using PowerShell -File, so signed-script enforcement on .ps1 files does not block startup.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">The wrapper resolves the repository root relative to its own location and fails fast when powershell.exe or the delegated launch-windows.ps1 file is unavailable.</scenario-2>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-CMD>
    <V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-BAT MODULE="M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-BAT" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The repository-root BAT entrypoint remains double-clickable and delegates to the shared root-level Python launcher instead of duplicating the Windows wrapper or launcher orchestration logic.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER-BAT>
    <V-M-ROOT-LAUNCHER MODULE="M-ROOT-LAUNCHER" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The root Python launcher delegates to the shared launcher dispatch command from the repository root and preserves the delegated exit code.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ROOT-LAUNCHER>
    <V-M-ROOT-LAUNCHER-SH MODULE="M-ROOT-LAUNCHER-SH" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_root_launchers.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The root Unix shell wrapper remains a thin entrypoint that executes the shared launch.py entrypoint through python3.</scenario-1>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-ROOT-LAUNCHER-SH>
    <V-M-MACOS-LAUNCHER MODULE="M-MACOS-LAUNCHER" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_unix_launcher_scripts.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_unix_launcher_scripts.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The macOS launcher script remains a thin orchestrator over the profile-aware Python launcher by reusing create-env, check-env, inspect, and exec flows instead of duplicating runtime resolution logic.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">The macOS launcher preserves Windows-flow parity by selecting the family first, supporting multi-model preparation inside that family, and exporting explicit runtime capability bindings for custom, design, and clone lanes before launch.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">The macOS launcher keeps system dependency mutation bounded to explicit opt-in Homebrew guidance while preserving the guided Hugging Face and Piper download paths for missing model assets.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">The macOS launcher keeps transient secret handling bounded to process-local HF and Telegram token prompts instead of persisting credentials to repository files.</scenario-4>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-MACOS-LAUNCHER>
    <V-M-LINUX-LAUNCHER MODULE="M-LINUX-LAUNCHER" PRIORITY="medium">
      <test-files>
        <file>tests/unit/scripts/test_unix_launcher_scripts.py</file>
      </test-files>
      <module-checks>
        <check-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/scripts/test_unix_launcher_scripts.py -m unit</check-1>
      </module-checks>
      <scenarios>
        <scenario-1 kind="success">The Linux launcher script remains a thin orchestrator over the profile-aware Python launcher by reusing create-env, check-env, inspect, and exec flows instead of duplicating runtime resolution logic.</scenario-1>
        <scenario-2 kind="success">The Linux launcher preserves Windows-flow parity by selecting the family first, supporting multi-model preparation inside that family, and exporting explicit runtime capability bindings for custom, design, and clone lanes before launch.</scenario-2>
        <scenario-3 kind="success">The Linux launcher keeps package-manager-specific install guidance manual-only and does not execute apt, dnf, yum, pacman, or zypper commands on the operator host.</scenario-3>
        <scenario-4 kind="success">The Linux launcher keeps transient secret handling bounded to process-local HF and Telegram token prompts instead of persisting credentials to repository files.</scenario-4>
      </scenarios>
    </V-M-LINUX-LAUNCHER>
  </ModuleVerification>

  <PhaseGates>
    <Gate-Migration-Phase-0 PHASE="Migration-Phase-0">
      <goal>Freeze migration baseline in canonical GRACE artifacts before implementation seams begin.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py -m architecture</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>docs/development-plan.xml, docs/knowledge-graph.xml, and docs/verification-plan.xml consistently describe migration target modules, critical flows, and verification references.</evidence-1>
        <evidence-2>No source-code architecture changes are mixed into the Phase 0 packet.</evidence-2>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-0>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-1 PHASE="Migration-Phase-1">
      <goal>Planning, request, and family seams land without breaking current adapter behavior.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py -m "unit or architecture"</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py -m integration</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Normalized execution-plan and planner contracts exist and are covered by tests.</evidence-1>
        <evidence-2>Server, Telegram, and CLI adapter boundaries remain intact.</evidence-2>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-1>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-2 PHASE="Migration-Phase-2">
      <goal>Qwen3 semantics are extracted into a family adapter with no external behavior regression.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_qwen3_family_adapter.py tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py -m unit</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py -m integration</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Qwen3 custom, design, and clone flows continue to pass through unit and integration verification.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-2>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-3 PHASE="Migration-Phase-3">
      <goal>The synthesis coordinator replaces central family semantics in TTSService without breaking persistence, logging, or inference guarding.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_tts_service.py tests/unit/core/test_job_execution.py -m unit</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py -m integration</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Planner/coordinator path preserves current transport-facing synthesis behavior.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-3>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-4 PHASE="Migration-Phase-4">
      <goal>Family-aware model metadata and compatibility paths preserve current Qwen3 manifest support.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_model_manifest.py tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py -m unit</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Current manifest v1 entries continue to resolve while family-aware metadata becomes representable.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-4>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-5 PHASE="Migration-Phase-5">
      <goal>Catalog, artifact, and runtime model responsibilities are separated with clear readiness reporting.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_config_and_bootstrap.py -m unit</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Readiness distinguishes declared, installed, loadable, runtime-ready, and loaded model states.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-5>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-6 PHASE="Migration-Phase-6">
      <goal>Runtime-oriented backend execution contracts preserve current MLX/Torch behavior through family adapters.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/test_backend_registry.py tests/unit/core/test_mlx_backend.py -m unit</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py -m integration</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Backends no longer expose only Qwen-mode-shaped generic interfaces.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-6>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-7 PHASE="Migration-Phase-7">
      <goal>Capability-based host-aware planning replaces simple platform-order backend preference.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/ -m unit</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/unit/server/test_health_routes.py -m unit</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Readiness shows accepted and rejected backend candidates with explicit reasons.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-7>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-8 PHASE="Migration-Phase-8">
      <goal>Second-family proof lands without transport rewrites.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/core/ -m unit</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/integration/test_api.py -m integration</command-2>
        <command-3>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py -m architecture</command-3>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Selected second family is recorded before implementation.</evidence-1>
        <evidence-2>Second-family support lands without introducing transport-specific branching in core.</evidence-2>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-8>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-9 PHASE="Migration-Phase-9">
      <goal>Platform support claims are backed by diagnostics, documentation, and available smoke evidence.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest</command-1>
        <command-2>TTS_RUN_SMOKE=1 python -m pytest tests/smoke/test_local_runtime.py -m smoke</command-2>
        <command-3>docker compose -f docker-compose.server.yaml up -d server</command-3>
        <command-4>docker compose -f docker-compose.telegram-bot.yaml up -d telegram-bot</command-4>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Support matrix in docs matches readiness and test evidence.</evidence-1>
        <evidence-2>Windows Docker Desktop evidence covers successful image builds plus live server probes on the validated host. Telegram Docker remains a documented compose lane, but this retained evidence set does not claim it as proven on this host.</evidence-2>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-9>

    <Gate-Migration-Phase-10 PHASE="Migration-Phase-10">
      <goal>Legacy transitional seams are removed only after the migration architecture is proven.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest</command-1>
        <command-2>python -m pytest tests/architecture/test_import_boundaries.py -m architecture</command-2>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Final docs and code describe the same stable architecture without stale transitional references.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Migration-Phase-10>

    <Gate-Phase-1 PHASE="Phase-1">
      <goal>Foundation modules have deterministic local checks and basic observability.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/unit/ -m unit</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>All foundation modules (M-CONFIG, M-ERRORS, M-OBSERVABILITY, M-METRICS, M-CONTRACTS) have passing unit tests.</evidence-1>
#PH|        <evidence-2>Phase 1 target-state docs explicitly name the HTTP server as the sole runtime/model host, Telegram as a remote HTTP client, HTTP as the canonical contract, and CLI as out of scope unless blocked.</evidence-2>
#DJ|        <evidence-3>Split-topology and anti-local-fallback checks are present in the verification plan and exercised by the server and Telegram gates.</evidence-3>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Phase-1>

    <Gate-Phase-2 PHASE="Phase-2">
      <goal>Core services wire correctly and pass module-local checks.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest tests/ -m "unit or integration"</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Backend selection, model registry, and TTS service have passing tests.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Phase-2>

    <Gate-Phase-4 PHASE="Phase-4">
      <goal>All transport adapters function correctly end-to-end.</goal>
      <commands>
        <command-1>python -m pytest</command-1>
      </commands>
      <required-evidence>
        <evidence-1>Full test suite passes including architecture boundary checks.</evidence-1>
      </required-evidence>
    </Gate-Phase-4>
  </PhaseGates>

  <AutomationNotes>
    <note>Telegram Docker remains a documented compose lane, but the retained evidence set in this session only proves the server Docker path. Keep Telegram Docker wording as runnable and documented unless a specific run also retains its own logs and external validation artifacts.</note>
    <note>`telegram-live` is a real Telegram Bot API reachability check plus remote-boundary summary, not server-execution proof or Docker parity proof by itself.</note>
    <note>Launcher/profile verification wording is synchronized to the landed unit-test wave: V-M-PROFILE-*, V-M-LAUNCHER, V-M-WINDOWS-LAUNCHER, V-M-MACOS-LAUNCHER, and V-M-LINUX-LAUNCHER describe only behaviors evidenced by the listed launcher/profile unit suites.</note>
  </AutomationNotes>

  <FailurePackets>
    <packet-template>
      <expected-fields>scenario, expected-evidence, observed-evidence, first-divergent-block, next-action</expected-fields>
    </packet-template>
  </FailurePackets>
</VerificationPlan>
